本剧改编自圣经  它们曾改变世界
本剧将始终保持《圣经》真谛
我已看见应许之地
And I've seen the promised land.
声音源自马丁·路德·金  美国民权运动领袖
在起初天主创造了天地
In the beginning, God created the heaven and the earth.
声音源自威廉·安德斯
美国第一次载人航天飞行的航天员之一
给谁的多 向谁要的也多
For those to whom much is given, much is required.
声音源自约翰·F·肯尼迪
美国第35任总统
你应当爱近人如你自己
Thou shalt love thy neighbor as thyself.
声音源自罗纳德·里根  美国第40任总统
你们找，必要找着
Seek, and ye shall find.
出自美黑人女诗人玛雅·安杰洛
你们求，必要给你们
Ask, and it shall be given.
上主的旨意怎样行在天上 就让它在地上实现
As the will of God is in heaven, even so let it be.
声音源自温斯顿·丘吉尔  二战时期英国首相
天主是我们的救助和力量
God is our refuge and strength.
声音源自贝拉克·奥巴马  美国总统
有史以来影响最深远的故事...
The most powerful story of all time...
至今仍在继续塑造我们的世界
continues to shape our world.
这是我们执政的基础
It's the foundation of our governments,
我们法律的蓝图
the blueprint for our laws,
人生旅程的神圣指南
a sacred guide for life's journey.
这就是——《圣经》
This is the Bible.
《圣经》
第一季  第01集
天主预先警告我  要我造一座方舟
God warned me. He told me to build a boat.
天主对我说
God has spoken to me.
他会领我们到新的家园
He will lead us to a new home.
他保证让我的后裔多如繁星
He has promised descendants as numerous as the stars.
-你是谁？  -我是梅瑟
- Who are you? - My name is Moses.
天主派我来  为使你们自由
God has sent me to set you free.
上主救我们脱离埃及 他许诺赐我们这片土地
The Lord brought us out from Egypt, he promised us this land.
很快  它就会是我们的了
And soon... it will be ours!
耶路撒冷  我们的新家园
Jerusalem... our new home.
达味  你在人间建立了天主的国度
David, you have forged God's nation on earth.
这个国度及其国民从全能造物主得到信心
A nation and a people find faith in an all-powerful creator.
天主与我同在！
God is with me!
他们的故事帮助我们认识自己
Their story helps define who we are.
如何选择
The choices we make.
如何生存  如何去爱
How we live. How we love.
如何奋斗和克服困难
How we struggle and overcome.
是谁创造了大地  海洋  和天空？
Who created the earth, the sea, the sky?
是谁创造了你们？
Who created you?
主啊！
Lord!
我们将此城献给上主！
We give this city to the Lord!
耶利哥是我们的！
Jericho is ours!
耶路撒冷城中所有的一切 随便抢！
And whatever's left of Jerusalem......help yourselves!
这是个圈套  他们想置我们于死地
It's a trap for all of us. They want us dead.
天主将从巴比伦带来灾难
God is bringing disaster from Babylon.
夫人  我相信您的儿子必是应许的那位为王者
Lady, I believe your son is the promised king of his people.
他叫什么名字？
What is his name?
耶稣
Jesus.
他的名字是耶稣
His name is Jesus.
你说有麻烦了
You said there was trouble.
人们都成群结队去找那个野人似的若翰
The people are flocking to this wild man, John.
他们认为他是先知
They think he's a prophet.
甚至有人认为他就是默西亚
Some even call him the 'Messiah'.
(默西亚 指受傅者 即预言中的耶稣
犹太人所期待的王)
即将到来的那一位  他将用火来施洗
There is one to come, who will baptize with fire
我不过是旷野中的呐喊
I am just the voice in the wilderness,
为主预备道路的...
preparing the way for the--
天主  我们要做什么
Lord, what are we going to do?
改变世界
Change the world.
玛利亚  他在这里
Mary! He's here!
-谁  -耶稣  他终于又回来了
- Who? - Jesus! He's back at last.
神贫的人是有福的 因为天国是他们的
Blessed are the poor, for theirs is the kingdom of heaven.
(《圣经》原文为 Blessed are the poor in spirit 此处按原文翻译)
温良的人是有福的 因为他们要承受土地
Blessed are the meek, for they shall inherit the earth.
你说什么
What are you saying?
你说你就是被天主选中派来人间的默西亚吗
That you are the Messiah, the chosen one sent by God?
已经开始了
It has begun.
倘若你渴望公义
If you hunger for righteousness,
通过我  必将达成所愿
you will be filled... through me.
有五千人前往见他  有五千人
Five thousand came to see him. Five thousand.
你们的王骑着驴来了
Your king comes to you, riding on a donkey.
他有点不寻常
There is something unusual about him.
没什么不寻常的  除了他有破坏一切能力
There is nothing unusual about him, apart from his ability to cause havoc.
如果一场骚乱  在第二天再次重演
If the disturbances that took place a day are repeated tomorrow,
我会将它粉碎
I will crush any rebellion.
在起初
In the beginning,
天主创造天地
God created the heavens and the earth.
天主说  有光
And God said, "Let there be light",
就有了光
and there was light.
天主将水和穹苍分开
Then God separated the water and the sky.
造就了海洋和陆地
He formed the seas and the land.
地上长出各类树木植物
Then he covered the land...with trees...and plants
水中有了各类生物
Then he filled the world...with all the creatures of the sea
空中有了各种飞鸟
...and of the air.
地上有了各种动物
all the creatures of the ground.
然后
And then
他创造了
he made
我们
us.
住在伊甸园中
To live in paradise.
直到
Until...
亚当和厄娃违背了主的旨意
Adam and Eve disobeyed God
偷食了禁果
and ate the forbidden fruit.
这一选择
And with one choice,
让他们辨识了善与恶
they learned both good and evil.
从那之后  因为加音杀了亚伯尔
Since then, since Cain killed Abel,
天主目睹了人类内心深处太多的恶念
God has seen too much evil in human hearts.
错误的选择  错误的决定
Wrong choices, wrong decisions.
导致了今日的悲剧
That's why this is happening.
我们的造物主决定净化这片土地
Our creator decided to cleanse the earth.
天主警告我  要我造一艘船
God warned me. He told me to build a boat.
一艘能拯救我的家人和所有动物的船
A boat to save our family, and all the animals.
而其他所有的生物
Every other living creature...
都将死亡
would die.
第七日
And on the seventh day,
天主
God...
休息
rested.
感谢YYETS字幕组
原始翻译时间轴及制作
天主教长沙青年团体重制
本字幕采用天主教思高译本
仅供福传学习
禁止用于任何商业盈利行为
如果你想为天主教的影视字幕出一份福传的力量， 请来Q群180574695【天主的译站】指导交流!
洪水吞没世界后
After the floodwater's engulfed the world,
《圣经》记载诺厄后裔有了全新的开始
The Bible describes a new beginning for Noah's descendants
这也是一个契机
and a chance to restore
人类与天主得以重修旧好
the relationship between God and humanity.
对全能造物主的全新信仰正在萌芽
A new faith in an all-powerful creator is being born.
在无数人信仰天主前
Before billions can believe in him
必定要有一人听到他的召唤
one man must hear God's voice
并且拥有信念追随他
and have the faith to follow.
亚巴郎  离开你的故乡
Abraham, leave your home
往我赐给你和你后裔的地方去
and go to the land I will give to you and your offspring.
我会祝福你
I will bless you.
我会让你成为万民之父
I will make you a father of many nations,
你的后裔将多如繁星
with descendants as numerous as the stars.
地上万民都要因你获得祝福
All the peoples on earth will be blessed through you.
撒辣依
Sarah.
天主同我说话了
God has spoken to me.
跟我来
Come with me.
我的侄儿  罗特  跟我们走吧
Lot, my nephew, walk with us.
亚巴郎
Abraham?
他将指引我们去新的家园
He will lead us to a new home.
但我们已经有一个很好的家园了
But we have a home, a good home.
远离城市  去一片新的陆地上
Away from the city to a new land.
为了我们的孩子
For our children.
但你们没有孩子  也永远不会有
But you have no children. You can never have children.
我们会有的
But we will.
他保证我的后裔会多如繁星
He has promised descendants as numerous as the stars.
他同我说话了  这是他承诺的
He spoke to me. He promised.
撒辣依  相信我
Sarah, believe me.
相信我
Believe me.
罗特  你要和我一起去吗
And, Lot, you are with me?
他会指引我们去一片神奇之地
He will lead us to a land of wonder.
不
No.
不要
真是神迹
Such wonder!
亚巴郎深信  他将成为一个大国之父
Driven by the belief that he will father a great nation,
他带领自己的小部落
Abraham leads his small tribe
前往天主与他立约的新地
to the land promised to him by God.
我还能做什么  别的土地都被占领了
What else can I do? All the other land is taken!
你不能抢我的
You can't have mine!
冷静
Calm down!
住手  走开
Stop! Come away!
不能再这样下去了
This can't go on.
你得告诉亚巴郎我们的决定
You've got to tell Abram what we decided.
怎么了
What's going on?
他的人想霸占我们的草地
His men are trying to take our pasture.
天主让我们共享这片地
God gave us this land to share.
那他应该再多给一些
Then he should have given us more of it.
告诉他
Tell him.
亚巴郎  土地不够
Abraham, there just isn't enough land.
我们人太多了
There are too many of us.
上主会给我们的  要有信心
The Lord will provide. Have faith.
相信看不见的天主吗
In a God we cannot see?
是时候分道扬镳了
It's time we go our separate ways.
不  我们必须团结在一起
No. No, we must stay together.
待在一起饿死吗
Stay and starve?
待在一起  眼看大家因一片草叶
Stay and watch our men kill each other
而自相残杀吗
over a blade of grass?
叔叔
Uncle.
我们打算离开
We're leaving.
那好吧
Very well.
你们想去哪里
Where do you want to go?
到索多玛附近更茂盛的草场去
To the greener pastures closer to Sodom.
索多玛？
Sodom?
保重
Take care.
亚巴郎没有自己的孩子
With no children of his own,
侄子罗特对他来说  就如同儿子一般
Abraham's nephew Lot is the closest thing he has to a son.
如果我连自己的家人都领导不了
How can I lead a people...
又如何去领导一个民族呢
when I can't even lead my own family?
一年后
快  帮帮他  是罗特的人
Quickly, help him! It's one of Lot's men.
撒慕尔  快
Samuel! Hurry!
来  靠在我身上
Here, lean on me.
发生了什么事
What happened?
我们毫无胜算  他们人太多了
We didn't stand a chance. There were so many of them.
罗特呢
And Lot?
还活着  但被抓走了
Alive, but taken prisoner.
帮他一把
Help him.
扶着我的手
Here, take my hand.
靠在我身上
Lean on me.
这样好受点
That's better.
好好照顾他
Tend to him.
我们有些训练有素的壮丁
We have some trained men.
亚巴郎  你们不是士兵
Abraham, you are not soldiers.
我告诉他们要相信天主
I told them to trust in God.
我让罗特跟我们一起来的
I made Lot come with us.
但后来他们离开了
And then they left us.
他们选择了他们的地土
They had their pick of the land.
那是他们的选择
It was their choice.
但他们是我们的家人
They are family.
我们必须帮他们
We have to help them.
天主会眷顾我们的
God will take care of us.
谁来帮我一把？
I think I'll need a hand on this one!
别碰她！
Leave her alone!
放开她！
Let her go!
Leave her!
信赖天主！
Trust in God!
罗特
Lot!
哦 罗特
Oh, Lot!
我们以寡敌众
So few of us against so many.
天主与我们同在
God is with us.
亚巴郎
Abraham.
我们还是要去索多玛
We're carrying on to Sodom.
我们聚在一处吧
We must stay together.
不
No.
不  叔叔
No, uncle.
我们不能回去
We can't.
我们得继续走我们的路
We have to carry on.
我们走
Let's go.
亚巴郎
Abraham?
进来吧
Come inside.
这么多星星
The stars.
-亚巴郎  -星星
- Abraham? - The stars.
满天的星星  来数数看
All of them. Count them.
-亚巴郎  -来数数看，数不尽的星星
- Abraham. - Count them, count them.
我们的造物主
Our creator....
他创造了星辰
...who made the stars,
也会赐给我们后裔多如星辰
will give us as many descendants
世代居住在自己的土地上
to populate our land.
他答应过  你会有孩子的
He has promised. You will have a child.
-我不会有  -你会的
- I won't. - You will!
不会
I won't.
我不能
I can't.
我的年纪太大了
It's too late for me.
但你还是有机会的
For you there's still a chance.
她
Her.
哈加尔
Hagar.
那个婢女
The servant girl.
不
No.
不  不行
No, no, no.
不可以
No.
可以的
Yes.
十四年后
快点
Come on!
拿稳了  依市玛耳
Hold it steady, Ishmael.
撒辣依  你看到了吗
Sarah, did you see that?
看到了吗
Did you see that?
我的好儿子
Oh! My boy!
My boy!
我的好儿子
My boy.
是你的好儿子
Your boy.
跟你妈妈去吧
Go with your mother.
亚巴郎
Abraham.
欢迎  我主
Welcome, Lord.
请进来说话
Please join me.
端水过来  为客人备好食物
Bring water. Prepare food for our visitors.
是  主人
Yes, master.
你们是远道而来吗
Have you traveled far?
是的  从很远的地方来
Yes. A long way.
亚巴郎  你的妻子撒辣在哪里？
Abraham. Where is your wife?
在帐幕里
In there.
明年  你的妻子撒辣要有一个儿子
Next year, Sarah will have a son.
你为什么笑？
Why do you laugh?
-我没有笑  -不，你实在笑了
- I didn't laugh. - You did.
孩子生下之后
And when you have a son,
要给他起名叫做依撒格
you will name him Isaac,
意为笑声
which means laughter.
感谢你的热情款待
Thank you for your hospitality.
我们得走了
We must go.
路上需要我帮忙吗
Can I help you on your way?
你们要去哪里
Where are you going?
去决定索多玛的命运
To decide the fate of Sodom.
索多玛
滚开
Get out of here!
索多玛变得堕落  成了罪恶之城
Sodom has become corrupt, a city of sin.
但我的侄子罗特生活在那
But my nephew Lot lives there.
他们全家都在那
He has a family.
控告索多玛的声音实在很大
The outcry against Sodom is great.
他们的罪恶实在深重
Its sins are very grave.
你们要毁灭它吗
You're going to destroy it?
整座城市？
The whole city?
好姑娘
Good girl!
你是公义的天主
You are a just God.
你真要将义人
Will you destroy the good men...
同恶人一起消灭么？
- This way. - ...along with the evil ones?
恳求你！  救命！
Please! Help!
救救我们！  救命！
Help us! Help!
假如城里有五十个义人，你还要消灭么？
What if there were 50 good people in Sodom?
不为其中的那五十个义人，赦免那地方吗？
Will they suffer the same fate as the wicked?
请救救我们
Please help us!
我们会考验他们
We will test them.
若是我的天使能在索多玛找出五十个义人
If my angels find 50 righteous people in Sodom,
为了他们我要赦免整座城市
I will spare the whole city.
-找到那些囚犯  -求求你  帮帮我们
- Find these prisoners! - Please, help us.
-他们往这边跑了  -救救我们
- They went this way! - Help us.
假若只有三十个呢
Or fewer? 30.
二十个
20.
你不会毁灭他们的  是吗
You would not destroy them, surely?
-求你了  -在那边
- Please! - Down there!
救救我们
Help us!
-拜托  -这边
- Please. - This way.
假如在那里找到十个义人怎样？
What if there were ten righteous men in Sodom?
你不存留他们么？
Would you not save them?
罗特  你做什么  他们是什么人
Lot. What are you doing? Who are these people?
他们需要我们的帮助
They need our help.
我会竭尽全力帮助他们
I'll do what I can for you.
即使只有十个
Even if I find only ten,
我也会赦免整座城市
I will save the whole city.
-这边  -给我出来
- This way! - Show yourselves!
那是什么？
What's that?
在门后面
Behind the door!
那边
Over there!
开门  开门
Open the door! Open the door!
把陌生人交出来
Give us the strangers!
把他们交出来
Bring them out!
-他们是我的客人  -让我们过去
- They are guests in my house. - Let us pass!
-别再纠缠不休了  -我们连你也不会放过
- Let them be. - We'll take you too!
开门  给我出来
Open the door! Show yourselves!
让开
Step aside.
-我们必须马上离开  -我看不见了
- We must go. - I can't see!
快点
Come on.
托亚巴郎的福  上主要存留你们
For Abraham's sake, the Lord is saving you.
一直跑 不要停
Keep moving. That's it.
等等
Wait.
他们在那儿
There they are!
我们走
Let's go.
要有信德  亚巴郎
Have faith, Abraham.
你们现在安全了
You are safe now.
你们必须离开  这座城市即将受到惩罚
You must get away. The city is being punished.
一直跑 不要停
keep moving. Come on!
一直跑
Keep moving.
一直跑  别停下
Keep moving. Come on!
不可回望这座罪孽之城
Do not look back at the city of sin.
相信天主
Believe in God.
不要回头
Do not look back!
罗特
Lot.
不！
No!
不要回头
Don't look back!
不要
No!
罗特之妻化为一根盐柱
Lot's wife is turned into a pillar of salt
因违背天主的话
for disobeying God.
罗特和他的女儿逃到山里
Lot and his daughters flee to the mountains
再也没有见过亚巴郎
never to see Abraham again.
她怎么样了
How is she?
是个男孩
A boy.
依撒格
Isaac.
如他所应许的
As he promised.
你们的面包
Your bread.
吃吧  依市玛耳
Eat your food, Ishmael.
依市玛耳
Ishmael!
-快来看  快来  -来了
- Come and see! Hurry! - I am!
做得不错
It's good.
撒辣
Sarah?
怎么了
What's the matter?
那个女人以为她的儿子会
That woman thinks her boy is going to inherit
承受应当属于依撒格的一切
what rightfully belongs to Isaac.
什么意思
What do you mean?
亚巴郎  我们一族的领导人会是谁
Who is to be the first of all our tribe, Abraham?
天上引领众星的星辰又会是哪一颗
The first star of all those stars in the heavens?
是我们的儿子
Our son?
还是她的儿子
Or hers?
-撒辣  我... -亚巴郎
- Sarah, I... - Abraham.
亚巴郎
Abraham!
你决定
You decide.
妈妈
Mama.
或者让天主来决定
Or let God decide.
勇敢一点
Be brave.
天主向他保证  哈加尔和依市玛耳会活下来
Assured by God that they will survive,
于是亚巴郎将他们送去荒野
Abraham sends Hagar and Ishmael into the wilderness.
再见了  依市玛耳
Goodbye, Ishmael.
哦 我的孩子
Oh, my boy.
我的孩子
My boy.
待你长大之后  天主会赐予你众多子嗣
When you grow up, God will bless you with many children.
十年后
我去给你做早点  依撒格
Let me make you some breakfast, Isaac.
历经多年奋斗  亚巴郎终于认识到
After years of struggle, Abraham has learned
被天主选中既是恩赐  也是考验
that to be chosen by God is a blessing and a test.
他必须证明他的信德
He must prove his faith
一次又一次
again and again.
祭献？
A sacrifice?
不
No.
我表现出来的信德还不够吗
Have I not shown you enough faith?
依撒格
Isaac.
多吃点
Eat up.
等你有了自己的孩子
When you have children of your own,
你就会想让他们长得高高壮壮...
you'll want them to grow up as big and...
亚巴郎
Abraham?
怎么了
What's the matter?
天主想要一个祭品
God wants a sacrifice.
我的孩子
My boy.
跟我来
Come with me.
父亲  柴火有了
Father, we have the firewood.
但是羊羔在哪里呢？
But where's the lamb?
上主会准备好祭品的  孩子
The Lord will provide a sacrifice, my son.
亚巴郎来问你要羊羔了吗
Did Abraham take a lamb?
没有  夫人
No, mistress.
把柴火拿来
Bring the wood.
父亲  你要做什么
Father? What are you doing?
父亲  你弄疼我了
You're hurting me, father.
依撒格
Isaac.
你一定要信赖天主
You must trust in God.
求您了
Please.
求您了  父亲
Please, father.
原谅我
Forgive me.
求您了
Please.
亚巴郎
Abraham.
祭品
A sacrifice?
哦 孩子  我的孩子
Oh, my boy, my boy.
我的孩子
My boy.
不
No.
依撒格
Isaac!
亚巴郎通过了最后的考验
Abraham has passed the ultimate test.
他将成为万民之父
He will become the father of God's nation.
接下来就到依撒格了
Now it's up to Isaac.
他会有一个叫雅各伯的儿子
He will have a son called Jacob.
天主会为他重新起名叫以色列
God will rename him Israel.
天主曾对他许诺的后裔如繁星般众多
The promise of descendants as numerous as the stars
渐渐成真了
is coming true.
但不久后  饥荒迫使以色列人
But soon famine forces the Israelites
远离天主许诺之地  下到埃及
far from the promised land to Egypt.
在那里  他们成为了法郎的奴隶
Here they are enslaved by Pharaoh.
亚巴郎和天主成了遥远的记忆
Abraham and God become a distant memory.
他的子民都沦为重负之下的役畜
All his people reduced to beasts of burden.
只有一人幸免于此
Except one.
梅瑟
Moses.
《圣经》下集预告
Next time on the Bible.
你不能再去争强斗勇了
You're not going to fight again.
我无法拒绝  母亲  他是法郎的儿子
I can't refuse. He's Pharaoh's son, mother.
还手
Fight me!
我命令你
I order you!
你根本非我族人
You're not one of us!
他在说什么
What's he talking about?
你生来就是个奴隶
You were born a slave.
你的族人就在外面  梅瑟
Your people are out there, Moses.
那些以色列人
The Israelites.
新生活欢迎你  梅瑟
Welcome to your new life, Moses!
你现在什么都不是了
You are nothing now!
你是亚巴郎的天主
You are the God of Abraham
我会去做  让我的子民获得自由
I will do it. I will set my people free.
如此水深火热
So much suffering.
等等  请等等
Wait. Wait. Please.
-你是谁  -我是梅瑟  若苏厄
- Who are you? - My name is Moses, Joshua.
天主派我回来  给你们自由
God has sent me to set you free.
你到这儿来做什么  梅瑟
Why are you here, Moses?
还我族人自由
Let my people go.
自由
Freedom?
他们能自由选择成为奴隶或是死亡
They're free to choose slavery or death!
我这一生都被法郎奴役
All my life, I have been Pharaoh's.
我再也不会是个奴隶了
I will never be a slave again.
若苏厄  天主与我们同在
Joshua, God is with us.
死亡天使会降临
The angel of death is coming.
滚  带着你们那卑鄙的天主
Go! And leave my land,
滚出我的国土
and take your wretched God with you!
梅瑟
Moses!
埃及人追来了  他们追来了
The Egyptians. They're here!
主啊
Lord!
跟我走
Follow me!
给我活捉梅瑟
Bring me Moses!
如果你想为天主教的影视字幕出一份福传的力量， 请来Q群180574695【天主的译站】指导交流!